<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dignitie of preaching in a sermon vpon 1. Thessal. 5.20. By Sam. Hieron.</title>
            <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120671</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855866</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855866</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21374</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21374)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1071:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dignitie of preaching in a sermon vpon 1. Thessal. 5.20. By Sam. Hieron.</title>
                  <author>Hieron, Samuel, 1576?-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 23, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Felix Kyngston for VVilliam Welby, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Swanne in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21374:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21374:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DIGNITIE OF PREACHING: IN A Sermon vpon 1. <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 5.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> SAM. HIERON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 10.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>How beautifull are the feete of them which bring glad tydings of peace?</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>BY PEACE PLENTY. BY WISDOME. PEACE</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by FELIX KYNGSTON for <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Welby,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Swanne in Pauls Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21374:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21374:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL KNIGHTS, SIR FARDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NANDO GORGES, Commander of his Maieſties Fort at <hi>Plimmouth,</hi> Sir WILLIAM STRODE of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi> Sir WARVVICK HELE of <hi>Wenbury,</hi> Sir CHRISTOPHER HARYS of <hi>Rad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and to the Worſh. GEORGE CHVDLEIGH of <hi>Strach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi> Eſquier.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT WORSHIPFVLL, Let it not (I beſeech you) be thought preſumption in me, to preſent that now to your view by Penne, which not long ſince, I commended to your eares by Voyce. I am, among many others, thankefull to God, who hath put it into your hearts, both to commiſerate, and to helpe, the ſpirituall neceſſitie of an vntaught Towne, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing the eſtabliſhment of a weekely Lecture in it. I hope, the Lord ſhall remember you in goodneſſe,<note place="margin">Nehem. 5.15.</note> according to that which herein you haue cared to doe for that people. And I doubt not but the ſoules which ſhall reape comfort by the ordinance of God, there, will bleſſe you, and God for you, acknowledging you his Inſtruments for their beſt Good. It is fallen to my lot, by your chuſing, to be one in this Preaching-courſe: when my firſt turne came, I thought it fitting, to hanſell (as it were) the Buſineſſe, by treating vpon the worth and neceſſitie of that ſeruice, which the reſt of my Brethren and my ſelfe, were there called to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge; that both they which wanted it, might vnderſtand their Hazard, and they which enioyed it might know their Happines, if they might be ſo happie as to embrace it. This thing thus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in by me, (according to my meaſure) though it was glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:21374:3"/> entertained by the moſt, yet by ſome it was not ſo wholly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of, but thought in ſome particulars, to ſmell too much of ſelfe-opinion. This hath moued me (contrarie to my firſt thoughts) to aduenture it by printing, vpon the Common Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. I haue deliuered nothing in it, but that which I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, partly in the Vniuerſitie, partly ſince by my poore ſtudies in the Country, and that from the chiefeſt for learning, Place, and Paines, in this our Engliſh Church; whereof I reioyce to be a ſonne, and wherein, it ſhall be my glorie and my crowne in the day of Chriſt to haue been employed as a Miniſter. Now, I am bold, to ſhroud it vnder your patronage, in as much as your cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me to a Turne in this Lecture, was the occaſion of its first Being, and you all likewiſe gaue countenance to it by your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, (according as you haue reſpectiuely done the like to vs al, and I truſt will doe ſtill) when it was deliuered. If you ſhall pleaſe to accept it as a fruit of my due reſpect to each of you in your places, it is all the recompence I looke for: In confident exſpectation whereof, I binde my ſelfe vnder my hand, to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Euer at your Worſhips ſeruice in the Lord, <hi>SAM. HIERON.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From</hi> VVodbury. <date>
                     <hi>1615.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21374:3"/>
            <head>THE DIGNITIE OF PREACHING.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. THESS. 5.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Deſpiſe not Prophecying.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE verſe next before this, I handled not farre hence, now well neere halfe a yeere agoe. My meaning was to haue there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo treated, both vpon this &amp; that which followeth, if there had been opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. But now, this Lecture being well begun, (and I pray God it may ſo long continue) and my ſelfe being called to beare a part therein, I thought with my ſelfe, I could not chuſe a more fit text, wherwith, to ſet on with this worke, it being ſo direct to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure honor to this preaching buſineſſe, which the gentlemen of theſe parts (for their own good and the Townes) haue ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſo deſirous of, and vpon which they profeſſe to haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance. I delight not to be long in preambles, I am come hither to diſcharge the dutie of a Preacher, not of an Orator.</p>
            <p>Thus then, it was <hi>Pauls</hi> aduice in the precedent verſe,<note place="margin">The coherence of the text.</note> to euery one ſenſible in himſelfe of the graces of Gods ſpirit; ſuch as doe accompanie ſaluation, to beware of quenching them, and ſo accordingly to endeuour to keepe life in them; yea and to adde more heate vnto them, by all good meanes. Now a ſpeciall meanes both to continue and to augment this ſacred fire, is here preſcribed, and it is this, not to <hi>deſpiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying:</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21374:4"/> ſo haue you of a ſhort text the connexion in ſhort.</p>
            <p>I cannot be profitable to you in diſcourſing vpon theſe words,<note place="margin">The opening of the words.</note> vnleſſe I make you to know what that is which is here termed <hi>Prophecying,</hi> and what not to deſpiſe <hi>Prophecying.</hi> In the ſtricteſt taking of the word, to <hi>Prophecie,</hi> is to foretell ſome future thing, and ſo accordingly they were anciently termed <hi>Prophets,</hi> to whom God reuealed his ſpecial purpoſes touching the after times. But now in the new Teſtament we finde this <hi>Prophecying,</hi> not ſo much to ſignifie a reuealing before hand, by diuine inſpirement, what touching States and Common-wealths, and particular perſons ſhall enſue, as an expounding the Scriptures in ſuch ſort as might beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance the common benefit. Me thinkes I finde in <hi>Paul</hi> an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act definition of <hi>Prophecying;</hi> It is a ſpeaking to men, to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, to exhortation, to comfort <note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.3.</note>. It is euen the very ſame which we terme, Preaching. I could countenance this inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, by the names of men, which deſerue reſpect, but <hi>Pauls</hi> deſcription is warrant enough: whatſoeuer any ſay, diſcouering their opinion touching this words meaning here, they ground vpon the place of <hi>Paul</hi> which I haue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Plowing therefore with the ſame Heifer, we may ſoone attain to the depth of that which may be thought the Riddle of this place.</p>
            <p>Now not to <hi>despiſe,</hi> here is to <hi>honor:</hi> for in this caſe there can be no third. He who doth not deſpiſe <hi>Prophecying, doth honor it,</hi> and he who doth not <hi>honor</hi> it, doth <hi>despiſe</hi> it. So that to come as ſoone as I can to the principall matter of this verſe, you may pleaſe to entertaine it as it is preſented you in this forme:<note place="margin">The generall doctrine.</note> 
               <hi>That the exerciſe of preaching ought to receiue from vs all esteeme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wouldeſt thou that the ſpirit of God, namely, the ſauing graces thereof, might bee conueied into thee and preſerued in thee? loe, God hath giuen gifts vnto men, and hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed them with skill of right diuiding his holy and ſacred word, Paſtors and Teachers for the gathering together of his Saints, and for the comfortable diſcouerie of the ſecret of the Goſpell: ſee thou hearken vnto theſe, and let their labour in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21374:4"/> the word, be ſweete and precious to thy ſoule. This is the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of <hi>Pauls</hi> counſell here, which now that wee haue found out, to the end it may bee more vſefull, I am now a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to enlarge. My proofe of this doctrine ſhall be made good by the declaring of two things. 1. That it is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe will and ordinance of God, that there ſhould be in his Church a certaine calling of men, ſet apart to this worke and ſeruice, of making the holy Scriptures vſefull to the people by the act of preaching. 2. That this act of preaching is ſo ordained by God, that wee haue no aſſurance in the world to attaine ſaluation but by it. Theſe two poynts well cleered, will take away all doubt touching this doctines truth. For if preaching be Gods ordinance, ſhall it not be honoured? and if we haue without it no hope of being ſaued, ſhall it not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue eſteeme? If then I ſhall be able to double theſe two two poynts, I ſhall hope to procure an eaſie paſſage for the maine doctrine into the heart and ſoule of euery one that heares me. So that you wil not crie when I haue done, as they did againſt <hi>Paul, Away with ſuch a fellow from the earth</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Act. 22.22.</note>, but rather breake out into ſome ſuch note, as theirs that followed Chriſt, <hi>Lord euermore giue vs this preaching</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 6.34.</note>. My firſt taske muſt be this, to make it to appeare, that God neuer purpoſed to leaue his holy word to be no more but read, either priuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in mens houſes, or publikely in our Churches; but appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there ſhould be men ordained, to expound the ſame by voyce, and applie it to the occaſions and neceſſities of the people for their edifying. For this is the ſoule of prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the very life of preaching. It openeth the Scripture, to ſhew what it meaneth, it fits it to the particular vſes and caſes of the hearers. Now that there hath been from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning a Calling of men to deale betwixt God and man in the things of God, the courſe of the holy ſtorie makes it plaine. In the daies before the flood (beſides that the firſt borne of euery familie was an officer of this kinde) we reade particularly of <hi>Enoch</hi> and of <hi>Noah;</hi> the one a Prophet by the teſtimonie of S. <hi>Iude</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iude verſ. 14.</note>, the other a Preacher of righteouſnes by the witnes of S. <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.5.</note>. In the following times, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21374:5"/> the ſmalnes of Gods Church for diuers yeeres, yet that which is ſaid of <hi>Melchizedech,</hi> that he was <hi>a Prieſt of the moſt high God</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 14.18.</note>, is an argument, of ſome ſuch ranke and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of men as I now ſpeake of. As the people of God mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied and began to put on the ſhape of a Body politique, ſo this courſe became more euident and more ordinary. Then the Tribe of <hi>Leui</hi> was deputed to a ſpeciall attendance vpon this function <note n="g" place="margin">Deut. 33.10.</note>, and from thence there was a continuall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of men ſitting in <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire vntill our Sauiours time. Chriſt when hee came did not ouerthrow this courſe, but eſtabliſh it. He appoynted Apoſtles firſt <note n="h" place="margin">Luke 6.13.</note>, they being by him inſtructed in the things which pertaine to the kingdome of God <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 1.3.</note>, and preciſe to ordaine nothing but that which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues had receiued <note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23.</note>, as they were diligent in reſpect of their perſonall induſtrie, ſo they appoynted ſuch as themſelues (in regard of the ſubſtance of their office) and gaue order (for the perpetuating of this courſe) <hi>to make choyce of faithfull men</hi> ſtill to be employed in this ſeruice <note n="m" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.2.</note>: and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith expreſly <hi>that Chriſt aſcended on high to giue gifts vnto men,</hi> euen that there might be ſuch for the gathering together <hi>of the Saints</hi> to the end of the world <note n="n" place="margin">Eph. 4.11. &amp;c.</note>. Now, as ſuch a Calling was of old, and muſt continue till time ſhall be no more, ſo the ſpeciall intendment was to teach. See for proofe in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Deut. 33.10. 2. Chro. 15.3. and in the new, Mat. 28.19. 2. Tim. 2.2. Therefore (as we gather by our Sauiours ſpeech to <hi>Nicodemus</hi>) they of this profeſſion were called <hi>Masters in Iſrael</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Ioh. 3 10.</note>, and after in the ſame ſort <hi>Teachers</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Eph. 4.11.</note>. The matter of their teaching was in the old Teſtament termed <hi>the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Law of God</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Deut. 33.10.</note>, and in the new it is ſaid to be <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer Chriſt hath commanded</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Matth. 28.20.</note>, and more briefly the <hi>Word</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">2. Tim. 4.2.</note>. The manner of their teaching in the old Teſtament, is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be <hi>reading in the booke of the Law, diſtinctly giuing the ſenſe, and cauſing the people to vnderſtand the reading</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Neh. 8.8.</note>: in the new, <hi>a publiſhing of the ſecret of the Gospell</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.19.</note>; <hi>a dealing vnto the people the Gospell of God</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.8.</note>. Now in teaching it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that there is a further matter then the publiſhing to the people, by reading from out of the booke, the words and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21374:5"/> of the Scripture. Euery ordinary man will quickly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſo much out of the nature of the word; Teach: Doth a Schoolmaſter teach his ſcholler in reading to him his Rule, vnleſſe he doe alſo cauſe him to vnderſtand it, and ſhew him how he may practiſe that which is the purpoſe of it? Doth a man of occupation teach his apprentiſe his trade, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding certaine generall precepts, if hee doe not diſcouer to him that which wee terme the Myſterie of his profeſſion in particulars? Thus farre we are come in the proofe of this firſt branch.</p>
            <p>It is the ordinance of God, that there ſhould be a Calling of men, to deale betwixt him and man, and that euery one called to this calling ſhould be <hi>apt to teach</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.2.</note>. He that wants this knowledge is no Prieſt <hi>for me,</hi> ſaid the Lord of old <note n="z" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.6.</note>. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing hereto is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wholeſome order of our Engliſh Church, in which no man is admitted Presbyter,<note place="margin">See the booke of ordination of Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons.</note> but he is firſt exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Biſhop, to conſider that his office is of great excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, and of great difficultie, ſuch as he cannot by any other meanes <hi>compaſſe,</hi> but <hi>with Doctrine and exhortation taken out of the Scripture:</hi> and then, after he is asked, whether hee is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to inſtruct the people committed to his charge with the Scriptures; in the end (a Bible being deliuered into his hand) he is willed to take authoritie to preach the word of God. And by the booke of Common Prayer it is manifeſt that none ought to adminiſter the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to the people, but he who may boldly ſay to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>If there be any of you which cannot quiet his conſcience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the Booke of Common Prayer, in one of the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to be ſomtimes vſed at the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</note> 
               <hi>but requireth further counſell or comfort, let him come to me, or ſome other diſcreete and learned Miniſter of Gods word, and open his griefe that he may receiue ſuch ghoſtly counſell, aduice and comfort, as his conſcience may be relieued.</hi> It is meant that hee ſhould haue ſomewhat in him, who muſt openly in the congregation make ſuch an offer. Our learned men doe in their writings deride that of the Popiſh Decretals,<note place="margin">Decret. p. <hi>1.</hi> diſt. <hi>28.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> Homilias per Circuitum anni Dominicis diebus &amp; feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatibus aptas.</note> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire little more of a Prieſt then to fetch out according to the rule of his Rubricke, the appointed ſeruice for the day. I muſt yet adioyne one thing more before I quit this branch,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21374:6"/> namely, that this is alſo Gods ordinance, that of this ſort there ſhould bee ſome in euery Towne, and that the ſame ſhould performe this Teaching-ſeruice euery Sabbath. The ordinance for euery towne may bee probably collected out of the ancient ſcattering of the tribe of <hi>Leui</hi> through all the land, out of that which is ſaid, that they (<hi>viz.</hi> the Leuits) taught all Iſrael <note n="b" place="margin">2. Chro. 35.3.</note>; and by that which is reported, that when Chriſt was teaching, there ſate by, Doctors of the <hi>Law, which were come out of euery towne of Galile and Iudea, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Luke 5.17.</note>: More directly by that, that <hi>Moſes was preached in euery citie</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 15.21.</note>; and the Apoſtles ordained <hi>Elders in euery Church</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Act. 14.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>: according whereunto was <hi>Pauls</hi> Iniunction to <hi>Titus,</hi> to conſtitute ſuch in each citie <note n="f" place="margin">Tit. 1.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. Hereupon came the terme of charges in the old Teſtament <note n="g" place="margin">2. Chro. 35.3.</note>, and of flocks in the new <note n="h" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.2.</note>. Then the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for euery Sabbath is iuſtly gatherable out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former ſaying, <hi>Moſes was preached in the Sinagogues euery Sabbath day</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 15.21.</note>; and it may be without violence concluded out of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of the Apoſtle to <hi>preach in ſeaſon</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">2. Tim. 4 2.</note>: what bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeaſon, then when the people reſt from all other ſeruices, and meet together in one place for holy duties? This courſe was held in the daies next following the Apoſtles. It is the report of <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> that in his time,<note place="margin">Iuſt. Martyr A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. <hi>2.</hi> Tertul. Ap. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Reading and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the word laſted an houre long euery Sabbath: and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> that there was not a meeting of the Chriſtians, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their ſoules were not fed with holy Sermons before they departed. It was a decree of the Councell of Mentz, vnder <hi>Charles</hi> the great, that there ſhould be a courſe taken, that there ſhould not bee one wanting, who ſhould vpon the Lords daies preach the word of God,<note place="margin">Iuxta quod vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus intelligere poſſit. Babing. <hi>on the Lords Prayer.</hi>
               </note> to the vnderſtanding of the people: With this conſents that opinion of Reuerend Biſhop <hi>Babington,</hi> of reſpectiue memorie, namely, that a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter can no more enter the Church vpon a Sabbath day without preaching, and not be guiltie of a damnable ſinne, then <hi>Aaron</hi> could goe into the congregation without death, in caſe, that at his entrance in he did not ſound his bels. And againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> vpon the Command.</note> he ſinneth the ſinne of a dumbe dogge, who paſſeth ouer the Sabbath day without preaching, and therein ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21374:6"/> the people guiltie of the prophanation of Gods holy day. Vpon this ground the Canons of our Church haue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that euery beneficed man (allowed a Preacher) ſhall preach one Sermon euery Sunday in the yeere: and againe,<note place="margin">Can. 45.</note> that euery Incumbent ſhall euery Sunday before Euening Prayer examine and inſtruct the youth and ignorant perſons of the pariſh in the tenne Commandements,<note place="margin">Can. 59.</note> the Articles of the beleefe, and the Lords Prayer. Theſe things I note to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent a conceit which ſome may haue, that I come hither to open a packe of Puritanicall ware, and to vent ſome priuate humorous opinions; you may ſee that that which I auouch touching the ordinance of God in this poynt, is the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Church. And thus haue I finiſhed the firſt part of my proofe, that preaching is Gods ordinance. It is his will that the ability for it ſhould be in euery Miniſter, and the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it in euery Congregation, euery Sabbath.</p>
            <p>The next part of my proofe is, that without dependance vpon preaching we haue no aſſurance of ſaluation. To make this manifeſt, I demaund, whether we beleeue the Scripture? <hi>that without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note>: and whether any other meanes be ſanctified by God to beget <hi>Faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the hearing of a Preacher?</hi> that, I am ſure, is ordained to that end <note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 10.14.17.</note>: as for any other mainly deputed thereto (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this) I am ſure there is no in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> euidence in all Gods book. The Lord hauing Saints to gather and to tranſlate out of the kingdome of darkneſſe, hath appointed and gifted Paſtors and Teachers to that end <note n="n" place="margin">Eph. 4.11.</note>: ſo much is apparant. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the promiſe of ſaluation is limited only to ſo many <hi>as God ſhall call</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Act. 2.39.</note>, (whereupon they which ſhall be ſaued are termed a <hi>called</hi> companie <note n="p" place="margin">Iude verſ. 1.</note>,) faine would I know whereto calling hath reference but to a voyce? What voyce ſhall wee thinke it to be, but that which ſoundeth in the publike Miniſterie? Chriſts voyce wee will all yeeld it to be, and ſo we may well, (<hi>for his ſheepe heare his voyce</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Ioh. 10.27.</note>:) and where is Chriſts voyce now, but in thoſe who by their calling are in Chriſts <hi>ſtead</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note>? and of whom hee hath ſaid plainly, <hi>He that heareth you hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth me</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Luke 10.16.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21374:7"/>
            <p>As we can haue no certaintie of our Election, vnleſſe wee <hi>giue diligence to make our calling ſure</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10.</note>: ſo what warrant hath any man to thinke hee is called, but by that meanes which God ordained to call the Gentiles? and what meanes finde we that to be, other then this? <hi>Goe teach</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Matth. 28.19.</note>, <hi>Preach the Goſpell to euery creature</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Mar. 16.15.</note>. What can be plainer then this? God hath <hi>reconciled vs vnto himſelfe by Chriſt, and hath giuen vnto men a miniſtrie of Reconciliation</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.18.</note>. We will ſoone yeeld that by this place it is proued that there is no comming vnto God the Father, but by Chriſt: ſhall it not be as ſtrongly proued thence, that there is no ordinary acceſſe to Chriſt, but by the miniſtrie? What moued our Sauiour to pitie the multitude being without a ſhepheard, (<hi>a laborer in the Lords harueſt</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">Matth. 9.36.</note>) was it not becauſe they were in apparant hazard of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being ſo deſtitute? Why is the land of <hi>Zebulim and Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalim</hi> ſaid to ſit in <hi>Darknes, and in the Region of the ſhadow of death,</hi> vntill the light of preaching ſhone among them <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 4.15.16.</note>, but becauſe the inhabitants were in the high way to hell, without miniſteriall inſtruction? Note that ſpeech: <hi>Iſrael, a long time, without God, and without a Prieſt to teach</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. Chro. 15.3.</note>. No Prieſt to teach, no intereſt in God. There is no Logick in the world to conclude otherwiſe. I am faine to ſtint my ſelfe in that which I could ſay in this argument. I heare what men ſay, when they be not able to elude the euidence of theſe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> They obiect and crie out, <hi>Oh Crueltie, oh Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme!</hi> now you doe damne all that haue no preaching. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> I ſpeake al this while of a way and courſe to which we are tied, and whereto wee muſt truſt, and out of which wee may not venture. I take not on me to preiudice the power or mercie of God, I will not for a world ſay in a pulpit, that there are none in heauen, which neuer heard a Sermon; I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Gods ablenes to ſaue as he pleaſeth, I know God can giue bread from heauen <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 6.</note>; he can make one ſute of clothes, or one paire of ſhooes to ſerue a mans turne fortie yeeres <note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 29.5.</note>; he can cauſe the earth to yeeld corne without ſowing <note n="e" place="margin">Iſai. 37.30.</note>; he can make one pitcher of oyle to pay a great deale of debt <note n="f" place="margin">2. King. 4.2.</note>. But what of this? no warrant hence for me to ſay, Husbandrie is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21374:7"/> not the ordinarie meanes of hauing Corne; ſowing &amp; men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ordinarie meanes to preſerue apparell; prouidence and induſtrie, and endeuour to get money, the ordinarie meanes to pay debts. Becauſe the Iſraelites were fed with Mannah, may I lie vnder a hedge in the Sunne looking till Mannah drop into my mouth? or becauſe Corne once grew without ſowing, goe fell away my Plough: and like <hi>Salomons</hi> ſluggard <note n="g" place="margin">Prou. 26.15.</note>, ſheathe vp my hands into my boſome, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce husbandrie: or becauſe of that of the Prophets wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, diſcharging debt by a pitcher of oyle; purpoſely runne my ſelfe into debt, many pounds, reſoluing to leaue to my Executor a Iarue of oyle to pay all; we would laugh at ſuch inferences, and think a man halfe mad, who ſhould make ſuch concluſions. And yet I know they are better a great deale then this; that becauſe wee doe not ſay they are all damned which haue no preaching, therefore Preaching is not the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained meanes to ſeeke ſaluation by, I ſay theſe concluſions are better, becauſe wee haue euidence of ſome, ſuſtained in outward things by ſuch vnuſuall meanes, but there is no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of any particular mans ſaluation without miniſteriall Teaching. As therefore notwithſtanding Gods dealing with the Iſraelites, with <hi>Hezechiah,</hi> with the widow, I may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, that he who truſts to be fed from heauen, ſhall be ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; and he who ſuppoſeth to pay his debts with a pitcher of oyle, ſhall rot in priſon: So he who thinkes to be ſaued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preaching, ſhall be damned. We muſt looke to what God bids vs doe, and not to what he in his abſolute power can do. Gods extraordinarie working is no impeachment at all to the truth of an ordinarie Rule. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> There be ſome which haue gotten that by the end, which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reports touching himſelfe, how that hee heard a voyce ſaying to him,<note place="margin">Confeſ. lib. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Take vp and reade, take vp and reade.</hi> And ſo taking the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he fell ſuddenly at the firſt opening of the booke vpon that place: <hi>Not in gluttonie and drunkennes, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note>. and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is ſuppoſed <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was conuerted: whereupon they would conclude a poſſibilitie of turning a man from the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of Satan vnto God without preaching. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> Hereupon I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21374:8"/> that who ſo ſhall ſay, that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was not conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vntill he heard that voyce, ſhall deliuer an vntruth. For it is plaine that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> had before that time been in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall affliction, greatly exerciſed with a combat betwixt the fleſh and the ſpirit, as appeareth plainly in the chapter going next before this, whereas he reports the matter of the Voice: And when this Voyce came, he was on his face weeping and at prayer, earneſtly confeſſing his ſinnes, and deſiring to bee deliuered from them. This Voyce is rather to be reputed a confirmation and perfiting of his conuerſion, then the proper inſtrument of working it. If wee would know whereby in deede he was conuerted, let himſelfe be heard, whoſe report this is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confeſ. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.14.</note> That being a Rhetorician, he came to the citie wherein <hi>Ambroſe</hi> was Biſhop, deſiring there to profeſſe Rhetoricke: while hee was there hee would needs goe heare <hi>Ambroſe</hi> preach,<note place="margin">Non vt docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem veri.</note> Not as a Teacher of the Truth, (ſo are his own words) for hee thought there was no ſuch to bee found among the profeſſors of the Chriſtian faith) but becauſe hee had vnto him ſhewed kindneſſe. Now marke what hee ſpeakes, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting his ſpeech to God:<note place="margin">Ad eum per te ducebar neſcius, vt ad te per eum ſciens ducerer. Omni die Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minico. Senſim &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcius.</note> 
               <hi>To him I was by thee led vnawares, that by him I might through knowledge be led to thee:</hi> and ſo he goeth on to ſhew how by hearing him, whom (as hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports other-where) he heard preaching euery Lords day, he was brought by little and little ere he was aware, neerer and neerer to the embracing of the truth. An excellent example for the confirmation of this point, that preaching is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes of a mans conuerſion. And yet I adde, that in caſe it were true, that the reading of that place had been the direct meanes of his Turning, yet it were nothing to the preiudice of that which I now teach, for I would ſay (and well I might) it was extraordinarie, and ſuch whereof we can make no Rule: and ſo indeed whenſoeuer any man is brought to haue ſauing grace &amp; true faith otherwiſe then by preaching, it is a courſe out of courſe, ſuch wherein God will ſhew his power and mercie, and the freedome of his proceedings; not ſuch wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he will haue vs ſimply and generally to relie. I returne then to my poynt, which is this: We haue no warrant to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21374:8"/> ſaluation any other way, then by dependance vpon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching; neither may we (to ſpeake of an ordinary courſe) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelues wee are in the way of ſaluation, vnleſſe wee be ſenſible of our being ſet into it by this meanes. God doth diuers things (as it it were) by way of preparing me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to grace: ſuch are afflictions, croſſes, inward affrightments; but when all is done, and ſpoken that can be, to this wee muſt come at laſt, that the maine worke (ordinarily) either by preaching it is wrought, or not at all. What an abſurd thing were it to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge preaching to be Gods ordinance, and yet to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie it to be ſimply neceſſarie to ſaluation, and to mince it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with (I know not what) faire termes, that it is good if it may bee had, and profitable for thoſe who haue no other helpes, and the like? Why? what make we of Gods ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? doe we account them only matters of conueniencie, and not of neceſſitie? For my part I know no more ſcripture for faith without preaching, then for ſaluation without faith; I am ſure the ſame ſpirit of God which hath ſaid, <hi>Beleeue that thou maiſt be ſaued,</hi> hath alſo ſaid, <hi>Heare that thou maiſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue:</hi> you would al crie out vpon me (and you well might) if I ſhould ſay, a man may be ſaued without praying; &amp; yet men are readie to account it halfe an hereſie, to auouch that a man cannot be ſaued without preaching: yet S. <hi>Paul</hi> linkes theſe together vpon one ſtring, <hi>Saluation, Prayer, Beleeuing, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Preaching, Sending</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 10.13.14.</note>. Men cannot be ſaued without praying to him that can ſaue: They cannot pray to him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out beleeuing on him; they cannot beleeue on him without <hi>Preaching;</hi> they cannot preach without <hi>Sending:</hi> and whom did God euer ſend, who was not able to diuide the word for the peoples edifying?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The things which God hath ioyned together let not man ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Matth. 19.6.</note>: we will grant the beginning, (no ſaluation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prayer, no praying without faith) but we will diſtinguiſh vpon the latter, (no beleeuing but by waiting on a Preacher which is ſent). Thus (I hope) albeit I haue not ſaid ſo much as might be ſaid in ſuch an ample ſubiect, yet I haue ſaid e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to confirme the two things which I vndertook: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21374:9"/> firſt, that preaching (vnderſtanding thereby, as before, <hi>a ſpeaking to men to exhortation, edifying and comfort</hi>) is Gods ordinance: Secondly, that hee hath not reuealed or warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs any other way of being ſaued; other helpes with this: all fruitleſſe and in vaine with the neglect of this. Theſe two things being true, ſhall not the maine doctrine be true, that the preaching of the word by men deputed of God to that ſeruice, doth deſerue eſteeme? Indeed as the whole wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God deſerues honor, ſo this ſeruice eſpecially, as being the chiefe of all the reſt. It is more excellent then the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacraments: <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent to <hi>preach,</hi> not to <hi>baptize</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.17.</note>, that is, to preach was his maine errand; for baptize ſome he did, which he might not haue done if he had not bin ſent. It is more noble then gouerning and the adminiſtration of diſcipline,<note place="margin">Apol pag. 3. ſ. 300.</note> becauſe (as ſaith the Reuerend <hi>Bilſon</hi>) God ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth his Church by the mouthes of Preachers, not by the ſummons of Conſiſtories: and <hi>Paul</hi> requiring <hi>honour</hi> to bee ſhewed to Elders ruling well, willeth it to bee ſhewed eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to thoſe that <hi>labour in the word and doctrine</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17.</note>, as the perſons employed in the better buſineſſe. It excelleth reading as much as the Apothecaries bruſing and breaking the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume doth the preſenting it in lumpe; the houſeholders cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the bread to the family, the ſetting it down in the whole loafe; the ſtirring vp of the fire, and the blowing it with the bellowes, the letting it lie couered in the aſhes: all which are the ſimilitudes to this end vſed by Reuerend B. <hi>Babington</hi> in his expoſition of that petition of the Lords Prayer <hi>(Thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come).</hi> It is more of worth then prayer: for what but preaching ſhall direct to pray? and whether in reaſon ſhall be thought more excellent, our ſpeaking to God, (which is prayer) or Gods ſpeaking to vs (which is preaching?) and looke 1. Cor. 14. and ſee whether <hi>Paul</hi> doth not preferre pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying before all other ſpirituall gifts, and makes it to bee the chiefe, euen where hee alſo ſpeakes touching prayer. If then the worſhip of God is worthie of reſpect, the exerciſe of preaching moſt of all, as being indeed the beſt of all. It is worthily reiected as a popiſh barbariſme by learned <hi>Morton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apol. p. 1. lib. 2. cap. 21.</note>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21374:9"/> that opinion, that the duties of the Sabbath ſerue not ſo much to edifie the people, as to ſerue the Lord: which the Papiſts maintaine for the vpholding of that abſurd propoſition, that the hearing of a Maſſe is to bee preferred before the hearing of the word. So that by the beſt of iudgement, the preaching of the word is reputed the maineſt part of Gods publike wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. I haue now done with the prouing of the doctrine. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way I hope it is cleere: Honour and eſteeme is the due of preaching.</p>
            <p>There is much matter by way of vſe to be deriued hence:<note place="margin">A double vſe. 1. For Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> Firſt, this concernes vs that are Miniſters: ſecondly, this concernes all good Chriſtians generally. Firſt for vs Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, this doctrine binds vs to maintaine by al good meanes the honor of preaching, &amp; to beware how we do bring this reuerend and ſacred ordinance of God into contempt; of all men, it ſtands vs vpon to endeuour that that may bee duly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed, which God commands not to be deſpiſed: It is the life and glorie of our profeſſion: it were a ſtrange thing if we ſhould not care to bring it into diſgrace: I ſay it is the glorie of our profeſſion: for when it may be ſaid of a man, hee is a Miniſter, but no Preacher, it is like that which is ſaid of <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">2. King. 5.1.</note>, <hi>he was a great man, and honourable in the ſight of his Lord, he was alſo a mightie man and valiant, but a Leper.</hi> This is a <hi>(But)</hi> which darkneth all the reſt: So that thereon I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, how much it behoues vs, to labour to vphold the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of preaching; becauſe to bee termed a Preacher, is the faireſt flower in our garland. Me thinkes I ſhould not ſay much of this: and therefore I will rather applie my ſelfe,<note place="margin">Three things by which a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſhal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. 1.</note> to ſhew how wee may ſaue this courſe from contempt, then to proue that wee are in equitie tyed thereunto. Thus then, there are three things by which a Miniſter ſhall aduance the honour and eſteeme of prophecying. 1. Diligence in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: It is that which <hi>Paul</hi> calleth in one place <hi>labouring</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17,</note>; in another, a being <hi>inſtant</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.2</note>; in a third, a <hi>preaching the Goſpell with much ſtriuing</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">1. Theſ. 2 2.</note>; <hi>It is the Lords worke</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.10.</note>, <hi>and curſed be he that doth it negligently</hi> 
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Iere. 48.10.</note>. It may be thought in the reaſon of fleſh and blood, that this is no meanes to make preaching
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21374:10"/> honorable, but to auile it rather; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> in as much as (according to the old ſaying) familiaritie breedes contempt; and excellent things when they once become ordinarie, are the leſſe regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. If Sermons were daintie, and mens ſtomacks were kept ſharpe, they would be more eſteemed. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> It is not ſo in this caſe, when the people are once brought to vnderſtand the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of preaching, (the neceſſitie, I ſay, both for ſaluation and for the worſhip of God, in as much as without it ſaluation is in hazard, and the worſhip of God is maimed) ſurely then, the more they haue it, the more they will honour it; and the more frequently the <hi>kingdome of God</hi> is preached, the more they will preſſe vnto it <note n="t" place="margin">Luke 16.16.</note>. Looke into experience, and ſee whether the ſeldomneſſe of this ſeruice doth not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme the people in their opinion, of the no great neceſſitie of it; which is the maine ground of contempt? Suppoſe a pariſh haue an Incumbent reputed learned, but yet remiſſe in preaching, ſhall not his ſlacknes cauſe the people to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> preaching is not ſo ſimply neceſſarie as it is thought? will they not ſay, Our Miniſter is learned and of iudgement, and <hi>knowes what is what; ſurely if preaching were ſo vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, hee would be more frequent in it then hee is?</hi> And what hath bred thoſe preiudiciall paradoxes to preaching, as that reading is preaching, &amp;c. but the indiſpoſition of men of gifts to be diligent in preaching? The vnwillingnes &amp; back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes of men to ſpend themſelues this way, hath cauſed (for the hiding of their ſhame) a ſtraining of wits, and a wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of Scripture, to proue the competencie to ſaluation of a reading Miniſterie: ſuch ſpurious propoſitions had neuer ſeene the light, if diligence in this dutie had vniuerſally been made conſcience of. Therfore we muſt yeeld that, that which old <hi>Latimer</hi> (a man who ſacrificed his life in Gods cauſe) once blamed vnder the witty terme of ſtrawbery-preaching, is a ſpeciall meanes to lay the honour of preaching in the duſt. It brings a ruſt, yea and a curſe vpon our gifts, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets a kinde of habite of idlenes, and cauſeth the people to reſpect that little which we performe but little: when I ſpeak of diligence, I doe not meane that a man ſhould be euer and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21374:10"/> anon in the pulpit: for there muſt be a time of gathering, as well as of diſperſing; and there is a kinde of mercenarie dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in ſome, which is meete to be reſtrained: but this is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence; a man is readie to take all occaſions to doe good; eſpecially bindes himſelfe conſtantly vpon Gods day to be buſied in Gods word. Happie is that ſeruant whom his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter when he commeth ſhall finde ſo doing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The manner of handling the word of God in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo as it is fit. <hi>If any man ſpeake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond way of hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</note> 
               <hi>let him ſpeake as the words of God</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.11.</note>: let him remember what hee hath in hand, and ſo deale accordingly. I remember how often <hi>Paul</hi> ſtands vpon his manner of preaching <note n="x" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.17.4.2. Theſ. 23.</note>: It is <hi>Hoſeas</hi> phraſe, <hi>the great</hi> or <hi>honourable things of the law of God</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Hoſ. 8.12.</note>; yet may theſe be ſo v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as that they may ſeeme baſe to thoſe that heare them. Woe be to that good meate that muſt paſſe the fingers of a ſlouen, before it comes to the mouth of the eater. I loue not to be forward to taxe any mans preaching, and therefore I will ſo ſpeake as ſhewing rather what may be, then what is. There may be a preiudicing and an endangering the honour of preaching in handling it, two waies: One is, too much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actnes: as when men ſtriue to haue euery word in print, and to ſtand in equipage; one neither higher nor lower, neither further foorth, nor more bacward then another; and doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect termes more then matter: embelliſhing their Sermons with the gleanings of all manner of authors, ſacred, prophane, any thing which may bee thought to ſmell of learning, and may raiſe an opinion of Eloquence, profoundnes, varietie of reading in the hearers. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> Will, I ſay, this make preaching to be deſpiſed? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> rather it is like to procure admiration and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, and to cauſe a kinde of aſtoniſhment in the hearers: happely it may for the preſent draw ſome ſuch ſuperficiall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to a Preacher, as that which is counted euen by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then a vanitie in <hi>Demosthenes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tully <hi>termes him</hi> Leuiculus Demoſthenes. Tuſ. Qu. Hic eſt ille De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes.</note> he ſaid it pleaſed him ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when as hee went in the ſtreetes, hee ſhould heare the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that carried water, ſay, <hi>There goeth eloquent Demoſthenes.</hi> Thus a man may be rewarded with ſome ſuch breath for this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21374:11"/> windy kind of preaching: but when it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to the touch, this ſhall bee found to diſhonour Gods ordinance in true iudgement. For what is that which indeed makes preaching honourable in the hearts of Gods people, but their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it, ſo as that they may feele the ſweetnes of it, and receiue comfort by it? That therefore which hindreth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding muſt needs expoſe this courſe to a kinde of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace: what contentment ſhal a man take in it, when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues but little what it meanes? It comes in our ordinarie congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to as little purpoſe (ſuch a kind of teaching) as that which is ſaid in the Prouerb,<note place="margin">Hic mulget hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, ille ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit cribrum: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>?</note> Where one doth milke a goate, another holds vnder a ſieue. It may bee the matter is good and excellent, but the hearer holds no more then a ſieue: becauſe nothing to any great purpoſe is vnderſtood. It is the pithie plainnes, which is the beautie of preaching. A text well opened, handſomely diuided, inſtructions familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raiſed, ſubſtantially proued by the Scripture, powerfully preſſed vpon the hid man of the heart, faithfully applied to the ſoule &amp; conſcience of the hearer. This is the courſe which makes <hi>manifeſt the ſecret of his heart, and brings him to fall downe on his face and worſhip God, and to ſay that God is in the Preacher indeed</hi> 
               <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>1. Cor. 14.25.</hi> Ferrum poteſt quod aurum non poteſt.</note>. It is truly ſaid that in ſome caſes <hi>Iron can doe that which gold cannot:</hi> and ſo that which is by ſome in their nicenes and curioſitie accounted but a blunt kinde of teaching, ſhall yet doe that which the more glorious, and gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring and gaudie courſe could not effect. <hi>The kingdome of God is not in word, but in power</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 4.20.</note>. I haue heard of a thing that fell out once at the Councell of Nice, where a Chriſtian of no great learning in eſteeme,<note place="margin">Ruffin. hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> conuerted a learned man, whom all the learned Biſhops with all their skill and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence could not perſwade: the partie wonne, brake out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe words: Oh you learned men, as long as the matter went by words, againſt words I oppoſed words; and that which was ſpoken I ouerthrew by the art of ſpeaking: but when in ſtead of words power came out of the mouth of the ſpeaker;<note place="margin">Non poterunt verba reſiſtere veritati (<hi>or,</hi> vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti) nec homo aduerſari po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit Deo.</note> 
               <hi>words could not withstand truth, nor man ſtand out
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21374:11"/> againſt God.</hi> Thus that plaine kinde of teaching, in which the euidence of the ſpirit is to be ſeene, works that which the more curious and refined eloquence could not doe.</p>
            <p>A ſecond way, by which in handling the word, preaching may be made contemptible, is in another extreame: namely, when the manner of dealing with the word is ouer ſleight, too looſe, and ſuperficiall; a man vents raw, ſudden, vndige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted meditations, ſuch as haue no manner of coherence, either with the text, or with themſelues: the text is rather torne, then diuided, rather toſſed, then handled; rather named (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the faſhion to haue a text) then followed ſo, as that the hearer may ſee the courſe, by which all is drawne from the text. Here a man makes a ſhift to rub out an houre, and to haue ſomewhat ſtill to ſay; he is much like the begger, of whom we ſay, he is neuer out of his way, though he be neuer in his way: ſo in this caſe, a man is neuer out of matter, though he ſpeakes neuer to the matter. This makes preaching ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, &amp; laieth it open (as it falleth from ſome mouthes) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a iuſt ſcorne. The common ſort happely eſpy not the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by and by, thinking all well ſo long as one goeth on; but the more aduiſed holding it vp, (as it were againſt the light) ſee the rawneſſe and raggednes and independance of that which is deliuered. It is an honor to a Sermon, when (as the ſaying is) it ſhall ſmell of the candle, and teſtifie for it ſelfe, that there was afore-hand care to deale ſubſtantially, and to approue our ſelues to euery hearers conſcience in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>The third thing to be taken heed to,<note place="margin">The third way for Miniſters to honour Preaching by.</note> that we may preſerue the honour of preaching, is our manner of life. An euill life in Preachers cannot but cauſe preaching to be vile: I call it an euill life, not when a man failes in ſome things; <hi>For in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things we faile all</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iam. 3.2.</note>: but when a man maketh it to appeare by his courſe, that he makes no conſcience of framing his life according to his owne teaching: is ſtrait in the pulpit, and in the ſtreete diſſolute. There is a great readineſſe in many to picke quarrels with the liues of the beſt Teachers, and no
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21374:12"/> doubt many things are ſlanderouſly reported touching ſuch. <hi>Cruell witneſſes ariſe vp, and aske things they know not</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 35.11.</note>: but when men taking the ordinance of God into their mouthes, ſhall yet walke like men hating to bee reformed, and runne into the ſame exceſſe with others, and be iuſtly taxable with open and ſcandalous euils; what can more diſhonour prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching? will it not cauſe it to be reputed a meere toy? A man ſhall be ſeene to perſwade to that, which himſelfe ordinarilie neglects; and to crie out againſt that, of which himſelfe doth make a common practiſe. <hi>Let no man deſpiſe thee,</hi> ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy:</hi> how ſhall that be? <hi>Be vnto them that beleeue an example</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">1. Tim. 4.12.</note>. I haue here a large field before me, but I would be loth to preuent my ſelfe in that I haue to ſay: and therefore I here ſhut vp this vſe, touching vs of the Miniſterie. Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſerues eſteeme, take wee heede how wee expoſe it to contempt. Our diligence in diſpenſing the word; our reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and well aduiſed handling the word; our endeuouring in the eyes of the people to frame our liues according to the word, ſhall vphold the credit of this worthie ſeruice: Men (though we do this) ſome will deſpiſe notwithſtanding, and ſpeake contemptuouſly both of vs and of our miniſterie: yet in doing it, they ſhall be as the Heretike, of whom <hi>Paul, who is condemned by himſelfe</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Tit. 3.11.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond vſe for al Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note>I am now come to the ſecond vſe, which concernes all Chriſtians more in generall: All that profeſſe to expect ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by Ieſus Chriſt, are bound to this dutie, to ſaue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching (as much as may be) from deſpiſing. This may be done (that I may not ſay all which might bee ſaid,<note place="margin">Two things by which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s may ſaue preaching fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contempt</note> but may inſiſt only vpon the chiefeſt) by two things eſpecially. 1. By a conſtant and an vnwearied dependance vpon preaching, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by all meanes poſſible to enioy it. Haue wee not reaſon to depend on it, whe,n <hi>where it wanteth the people periſh</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Prou. 29.18.</note>? And ſhall we not honour it exceedingly, when our feet ſhall euen weare out the threſhold of that houſe, where it is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſpenſed? and when we ſhall ſeeke knowledge at the lips of the Prieſts with ſuch earneſtnes, as if wee were guided
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21374:12"/> by that ſpirit which was in thoſe primitiue Conuerts, that cried out to <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt, <hi>Men and brethren what ſhall we doe</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note>? It will appeare that wee eſteeme Gods ordinance, when wee ſhall for the ſake of it neglect our profit, hazard our outward peace, ſeeme careleſſe of our credit, ſtraine our purſes, and be like the Merchant in the Goſpell, that part's with all that hee hath for one ſpeciall <hi>Pearle</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Matth. 13.46.</note>. Great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt is caſt vpon prophecying at this day, by default here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; I will not ſo much ſpeake of thoſe who caſt no manner of reſpect vnto it, but openly and ordinarily, and in a ſort pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly doe auile it; but of thoſe which make ſome ſhow to eſteeme it. That is moſt pitifull when ſuch as pretend a kinde of honour, ſhall yet by conſequent be found deſpiſers. Firſt ſome would (as they make ſhow) waite on this meanes, but they will make their own conditions: prouided that it comes home to them; that they may haue it without trouble: Oh how glad would they be, had they a Preacher in their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; they would thinke it to be none of the ſmalleſt portions of their happineſſe? But when it comes to the poynt of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out and of trauelling to the Prophet with the Shuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite <note n="i" place="margin">2. King. 4.</note>; or elſe of cutting off ſome of their ſuperfluities, and of ſtinting themſelues in other things, that they may draw to them ſome able Miniſter of the new Teſtament; then they begin to be as backward and ſorrowfull as the rich man in the Goſpell, who as forward as hee ſeemed at firſt, yet began to flinch, when hee heard the charge of <hi>ſelling;</hi> and ſo they, after a large commendation of preaching, and a faire tale of their eſteeming it, yet while they are afraid of trouble, and reproch, and labour, and are loth to be at any charges, they ſtill content themſelues with an vnable miniſterie. Here is a faire honour done to preaching. For ſhame, if our hearts bee to it, (as woe be to vs if they be not) let vs engage our ſelues for it. Remember what hath been both ſaid and prooued, there is no other ordinarie way of ſaluation: and wilt thou not ſtraine thy body, thy purſe, thy credit; aduenture thy out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace; doe any thing that thou maiſt be ſaued? It is no honoring of the ordinance of God, if thou canſt any way ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21374:13"/> and content thy ſelfe without it. I ſhall be thought (perhaps to perſwade ſtrange things, and (as may be thought) not iuſtifiable. But doe me right, I pray you, in indifference, conſidering what I ſay: Behold Luk. 6.17. and marke what you finde there: <hi>A great multitude of people out of all Iudea, and Ieruſalem, and from the ſea coaſts of Tyre and Sidon which came to heare him.</hi> Did theſe ſay, <hi>If this good man would come to vs, how glad ſhould we be?</hi> but they went out to him, they left their blind guides and followed this <hi>Seer</hi> where he was, I demaund; Is not this written for our learning? Can we ſay, it was not well that they did? were they not worthie of praiſe for ſo doing? Then ſay I with the Apoſtle, <hi>Whatſoeuer things are honeſt and of good report, thoſe things doe</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Phil. 4 8.</note>. And if this ſatisfie not, and you ſuſpect my iudgement, I pray looke into the booke you haue in your pariſhes, the Workes of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Iewell,</hi> in his Sermons vpon this chapter, and vpon the 12. and 13. verſes: what ſhall wee ſay of them that labour not, that doe neither teach, nor exhort, nor reproue, nor cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect; that haue no care to doe their meſſage; and no regard to the people, what may I ſay of ſuch? God himſelfe ſaith, <hi>They are dumbe dogges that cannot barke, they lie and ſleepe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in ſleeping, they all looke to their owne way, and their owne aduantage, and euery one for his owne purpoſe</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iſai. 56.10.11.</note> Chriſt calleth them Theeues and Robbers. They are vnſauourie ſalt, profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for nothing, but to be caſt foorth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oden vnder feet of men. <hi>Woe is vnto me</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) if I preach not the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.16.</note>. Woe to the ſeruant that wrappeth his tallent in a nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, and increaſeth not his Maſters gaine. God grant ſuch idle and ſlothfull Miniſters grace to know their office, and to doe it: If not, God giue the people grace to know them, and to ſhunne them, and to flie from them. (So farre he:) Which words if they doe not teach, not to be ſatisfied without prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and to ſhunne thoſe which are vnſufficient, and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in that dutie, for my part I muſt acknowledge I doe not vnderſtand Engliſh. Let this then be our honour giuen to preaching, euen to ſtriue that we may enioy it, and to put our ſelues to hard conditions, rather then to want it. And doe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21374:13"/> you of this towne particularly take notice of it; ſee how God hath moued the hearts of the Worſhipful of theſe parts, to pitie your neceſſitie; and to procure a courſe of preaching with you, not ſo much that you might reſt content with this, or ſay as <hi>Micah</hi> the Ephramite, when he had got a Leuite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his houſe, <hi>Now I know that the Lord will doe me good, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I haue a Leuit to my Prieſt</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iudg. 17.13.</note>; ſo now, <hi>We are ſafe, we haue a Lecture in our towne.</hi> No, if you ſhall not ſet together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your ſelues, to haue it amongſt you on the Sabbath day, the day principally deputed to this ſeruice, for my part I ſhall thinke our paines here (in reſpect of you) to be vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</p>
            <p n="2">2, There is another kinde of dependance, which is alſo preiudiciall to the honor of preaching, and that is that which is but by fits &amp; ſtarts; ſomewhat eger happely at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but ſlaking by degrees, till it come to nothing: you will diſgrace it here much, if filling the Church now at the firſt, you ſhall hereafter, like men whoſe ſtomackes are full, begin to grow wearie and full of that which you now ſeeme to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Giue vs not occaſion to ſay hereafter as Chriſt of <hi>Iohn; He was a burning and a ſhining light, and you were willing for a ſeaſon to reioyce in this light</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">Ioh. 5.35.</note>. It is a thing to be ſuſpected: experience ſheweth, that (as the ſaying is) euery thing is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie when it is young; ſo ſuch exerciſes as theſe, are flocked vnto at the firſt, but after, men by little and little fall off: ſome will heare onely this man, ſome onely that man; ſome onely now and then, when they haue occaſion to come to towne; ſome neuer a whit: You will bring a diſgrace vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our paines here, if you ſhall cauſe it to be thought that wee haue cloyed your ſtomackes, and taken away the edge of your appetites. <hi>Haue not the faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt the Lord of glorie with reſpect of perſons</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Iam. 2.1.</note>: make much of, and honor any mans endeuours that doth his dutie vpon his conſcience. This ſhall be your firſt way of honoring preaching; your manner of dependance vpon it let it be earneſt, painfull, conſtant; let it appeare that you will not hope to be ſaued, but by the meanes that God hath ſanctified.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21374:14"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond way of hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring preaching by common Chriſtians.</note>The ſecond way by which you ſhall honour preaching, is, yeelding obedience to that which is taught, and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in life to our preaching. It is not the bare <hi>hearer, but the doer</hi> withall that ſhall be <hi>bleſſed</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Iam. 1.25.</note>. There is no fouller ſtaine to preaching, then when they which ſay they loue it, and deſire it, and eſteeme and follow after it, and trauaile to enioy it, ſhall yet make no conſcience of obedience to it: How doth this open the mouthes of gain-ſaiers, and embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them to their imputations vpon preaching, when they ſhall haue ſome colour to crie out, <hi>there be none worſe, more proud, wanton, contentions, couetous, oppreſſing, fraudulent, then the greateſt hearers?</hi> when you walke not according to the rules you are taught, you make preaching and profeſſing to be reputed the nurſerie of vngodlineſſe, and the couert for all villanie. And therfore, you that are of the firſt ſort, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Iuſtices, who haue laboured to draw Preachers hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and who now giue countenance to vs by your preſence, honour vs alſo (I pray you) with your holy practiſe: make it to appeare by your zealous execution of Iuſtice, when you ſit here vpon the buſineſſe of the Countrey, by your ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of groſſe diſorders, and that world of Alehouſes, that is, and which is the very neaſt of all wickednes; and by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of your followers and families; and principally by the Chriſtian cariage of your ſelues; and by the abatement of your exceſſes, vaine pleaſures, Epicuriſmes, ſwearings, and ſuch like, that you haue not drawne preaching hither for a forme, or out of a glorie; but that in ſinceritie of heart, you haue ſought your owne furtherance in the waies of pietie. Let it not be ſaid, (as it will be, if you preuent it not) <hi>Behold, here be ſuch and ſuch, euery weeke at Sermon, and yet how doe they liue rather as Atheiſts, and enemies to Religion, then as godly Chriſtians?</hi> And you of the towne, who ſeeme to bee glad of this erected courſe, reſolue with your ſelues that you will ſet on with a generall reformation. Let vs ſee ſome fruit by our labours with you: giue no cauſe to haue it thought, you reioyce in this for outward reſpects; as to encreaſe, your Market; and to draw companie to your towne, or to vent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21374:14"/> your commodities; or that you may glorie; <hi>Oh wee haue a Lecture too, as well as ſuch a towne, or as ſuch:</hi> but as other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning townes ſhall be beholding to you, for borrowing from your Church the light of <hi>Doctrine;</hi> ſo let them receiue from you the light of good example. And you all, whether Gentlemen or Yeomen, or whatſoeuer elſe, I beſeech you in the feare of God, receiue not this grace of God in vaine; make ſome vſe of your comming; learne to practiſe that, by which your families through you may be bettered; your neighbors prouoked, eſpecially your owne ſoules comforted in the day of Chriſt. Let not the Lecture-day (now when the Sermon is ended) be made a day of voluptuouſnes, of quaffing, ſwagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, diſorder; goe not from the Church to eate out, and eate vp one another in the Market, by fraud and crueltie: <hi>Runne not euery man to his raſe, as a horſe to the battell,</hi> but let vs haue comfort to ſpend our ſpirits among you, when we ſhall behold your good conuerſation in Chriſt, that wee all both Preachers and hearers may reioyce together at the laſt day, that we haue not runne in vaine. If you faile in this, it is not your comming to heare vs, your commending vs, your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue ſaluting vs, your prouiding to entertaine vs, that can honour our miniſterie: we ſhall (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this complement) hang downe our heads with ſhame and ſay; You haue requited our labour with intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erable contempt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Wodbury,</hi> firſt of Auguſt. 1615.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21374:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21374:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
